Moritz Böhle

PHD STUDENT · MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR INFORMATICS

■ moritzboehle@me.com | • moboehle | • moritz-boehle

Research statement

My research is focused on interpretable, trustworthy, and responsible deep learning. In particular, over the course of my PhD, I investigated how to design *inherently interpretable* deep neural networks such as the CoDA and the B-cos Networks, which are optimised to inherently provide explanations that highlight important input features.

Education _____

Max Planck Institute for Informatics

Saarbrücken

PhD in Interpretability in Deep Learning

03/2019 - present

Advisors: Prof. Dr. Bernt Schiele, Prof. Dr. Mario Fritz

Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience

Berlin

MSc Computational Neuroscience, GPA 1.0 (Best possible: 1.0)

10/2016 - 01/2019

Machine Learning · Models of Higher Brain Functions · Models of Neural Systems

Thesis: Noise Suppression and Speech Enhancement using Deep Learning. Grade: 1.0/1.0

University of California, Santa Cruz

Santa Cruz, CA, USA

UC EDUCATION ABROAD PROGRAM, GPA 4.0 (BEST POSSIBLE: 4.0)

10/2014 - 06/2015

Programming in Java, C, C++ · Biophysics

Freie Universität Berlin

Berlin

BSC PHYSICS, GPA 1.0 (BEST POSSIBLE: 1.0)

01/2012 - 08/2016

Linear Algebra · Analysis · Analytical Mechanics · Statistical Physics

Thesis: Evaluating different barrier-crossing theories using Langevin simulations. Grade: 1.0/1.0

Research and Publications _____

(* EQUAL CONTRIBUTION)

- A. Parchami-Araghi*, **M. Böhle***, S. Rao*, B. Schiele. *Good Teachers Explain: Explanation-Enhanced Knowledge Distillation.* **Under submission.**
- 2023 S. Gairola, **M. Böhle**, F. Locatello, B. Schiele. *Investigating the Interpretability of Self-Supervised Visual Pretraining.* **Under submission.**
- 2023 **M. Böhle**, N. Singh, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *B-cos Alignment for Inherently Interpretable CNNs and Vision Transformers.* arXiv:2306.10898. **Under submission.**
- 2023 S. Rao, **M. Böhle**, B. Schiele. *Better Understanding Differences in Attribution Methods via Systematic Evaluations.* arXiv:2303.11884. **Under submission.**
- 2023 S. Rao*, **M. Böhle***, A. Parchami-Araghi, B. Schiele. *Studying How to Efficiently and Effectively Guide Models with Explanations*. International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV), 2023.
- A. Kukleva*, **M. Böhle***, B. Schiele, H. Kuehne, C. Rupprecht. *Temperature Schedules for self-supervised contrastive methods on long-tail data*. International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2023.
- 2022 **M. Böhle**, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability.* Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), 2022.
- S. Rao, **M. Böhle**, B. Schiele. *Towards Better Understanding Attribution Methods*. Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), 2022.
- 2022 **M. Böhle**, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *Optimising for Interpretability: Convolutional Dynamic Alignment Networks.* IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2022.

M. Böhle, M. Fritz, B. Schiele. *Convolutional Dynamic Alignment Networks for Interpretable Classifications*. Conference on Computer Vision and Patter Recognition (CVPR), oral, 2021.

M. Böhle*, F. Eitel*, M. Weygandt, K. Ritter. *Layerwise Relevance Propagation for Explaining DNN Decisions in MRI-based Alzheimer's Disease Classification*. **Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience** 11 (2019): 194.

Professional Experience ____

2019

05/2018 - 12/2018 Deep Learning Researcher, Audatic GmbH, Berlin

10/2017 - 05/2018 **Software Development**, Digital Unit Volkswagen Financial Services AG, Berlin 01/2012 - 10/2012 **Software Development and Quality Management**, Tembit Software GmbH

Academic Activities -

07/2023 - present Co-supervision PhD student, Collaboration with N. Pham, S. Rao, B. Schiele.

Concept-based explanations of Deep Neural Networks.

06/2023 - present Co-supervision MSc student, Collaboration with S. Arya, S. Rao, B. Schiele.

Increasing the interpretability of conventional Deep Neural Networks

11/2022 - present Co-supervision PhD student, Collaboration with S. Gairola, F. Locatello, B. Schiele.

Interpretable self-supervised, object-centric learning

01/2022 - present Co-supervision MSc student, Collaboration with A. Parchami-Araghi, S. Rao, B. Schiele.

Explanation-based Knowledge Distillation

01/2021 - present Co-supervision PhD student, Collaboration with S. Rao, B. Schiele.

Better understanding and utilising attribution-based model explanations

05/2021 - 10/2021 Co-supervision BSc student, Collaboration with N. Singh, D. Stutz, B. Schiele.

Exploring the relationship between robustness and interpretability

04/2020 - 03/2021 **Teaching Assistant**, Elements of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence, B. Schiele.

03/2019 - present Reviewing activities, IEEE PAMI, CVPR, ECCV, ICLR, NeurIPS, IEEE Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur., ICML

10/2015 - 09/2016 **Teaching Assistant**, Linear Algebra and Analysis, R. Klein

Invited Talks_

03/2023 Spotlight @ Explainability in Machine Learning Workshop, Tübingen.,

Towards B-cos Deep Neural Networks as the new default

06/2022 Spotlight @ XAI for Computer Vision (XAI4CV) workshop, CVPR.,

B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability

12/2021 Invited talk @ Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT).,

B-cos Networks: Alignment is All We Need for Interpretability

Scholarships, Awards, Grants_

10/2022 Outstanding Reviewer, ECCV 2022

01/2015 - 03/2019 Full scholarship, German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des Deutschen Volkes)

10/2014 - 12/2014 Sudy abroad scholarship, DAAD PROMOS program

Travel grant, Fulbright program

Extra-curricular activities

05/2021 - present PhD student representative, Computer Vision and Machine Learning department, MPI for Informatics

04/2017 - 01/2019 MSc student representative, Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience

2